James S. and Frances M. Bradford Collection 1749-1898 Mss.B.F85.bra
American Philosophical Society
James S. and Frances M. Bradford Collection
1749-1898
Mss.B.F85.bra
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
The James S. and Frances M. Bradford Collection contains a wealth of letters to and from Polly Stevenson Hewson, intimate friend of Benjamin Franklin. At the heart of the collection are approximately 40 letters from Mary Stevenson to Franklin with a smaller number in return. Friendly, increasingly intimate, these provide a glimpse of the domestic life of Franklin and his warm personal relations with the Stevensons and Hewsons. Among the noteworthy individual items is the manuscript "Craven Street Gazette" (Sept. 22-26, 1770), the mock newspaper Franklin produced while in London. The collection also contains a series of unrelated miscellaneous manuscripts that includes correspondence from William Bradford, Patrick Henry, and George Washington.
Bradford, Frances Mary
Bradford, James S.
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
Related Archival Materials note
Polly Hewson appears as a correspondent in several other collections at the APS, including: Benjamin Franklin Papers (B F85); Benjamin Franklin Miscellaneous Collections (B F85x); Bache Family Papers (B B121);Sarah Franklin Bache (B B1245);Hewson Family Papers (B H492).
Separated Materials note
The Bradford Family Collection included several items that have been transferred to the Curatorial Department or Department of Printed Materials. These include: Miniature chess set and board used by Mary Stevenson Hewson, Memorial ring "John Hawkesworth,LLD ob 17 Nov. 1773 art 58" formerly owned by Hewson, Pluche, Noel Antoine, "Spectacle de la nature...," 8th ed. (London, 1753-1757). Presentation copy from Franklin to Hewson, 500 P72s.8 v.1-7.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of James S. and Frances M. Bradford, 1956 and 1960.
Scope and Contents note
The James S. and Frances M. Bradford Collection contains a wealth of letters to and from Polly Stevenson Hewson, intimate friend of Benjamin Franklin. At the heart of the collection are approximately 40 letters from Mary Stevenson to Franklin with a smaller number in return. Friendly, increasingly intimate, these provide a glimpse of the domestic life of Franklin and his warm personal relations with the Stevensons and Hewsons. Among the noteworthy individual items are the manuscript "Craven Street Gazette" (Sept. 22-26, 1770), the mock newspaper Franklin produced while in London, Franklin's "Scheme for a new alphabet" (1768), and his parable on brotherly love (1774).
The Bradford Collection also includes a number of interesting letters between Hewson and Dr. John Hawkesworth, as well as a few miscellaneous letters from important Americans owned by the Bradford family, including two from George Washington and two from Patrick Henry. A self-educated miscellaneous writer, Hawkesworth was associated with Samuel Johnson (until a falling out in about 1756) and was a contributor to the "Gentleman's Magazine," the "Adventurer," which he edited with Johnson), and other publications, and edited a volume describing Captain Cook's voyage to the South Seas. He and his wife were close friends of Hewson and of Franklin.
The collection also contains a series of typescripts of letters written between Hewson and Franklin, several of which appear in the original in the collection.
Frances Margaret Bradford presented a third series of papers in 1960. In addition to further correspondence and estate material concerning Margaret Stevenson and Mary Hewson, this series also contains some miscellaneous, and unrelated, correspondence from William Bradford, Patrick Henry, and George Washington.
Arrangement note
Series I. is physically arranged in order of correspondent, but is presented here in chronological order.
Biographical/Historical note
During the 17 years he served as colonial agent for Pennsylvania in London, Benjamin Franklin developed a strong attachment to the family of his landlady at 36 Craven Street, Margaret Stevenson. Margaret's daughter, Mary (usually called Polly) became a particular intimate, so much so that Franklin connived to marry her off to his son, William. Although nothing came of these efforts, Franklin's intentions did little to impair the friendship with the Stevensons, and Franklin's domestic circle at Craven Street eventually grew to include his grandson William Temple Franklin and Sarah Franklin, daughter of an English cousin.
In 1770, Polly married the distinguished surgeon and anatomist William Hewson in what was to be a tragically short pairing. Hewson died in 1774 after contracting septicaemia from a cut he received while dissecting a cadaver in his basement, leaving Polly to care for their daughter and two sons to raise, one of whom was Franklin's godson. Recognizing the difficulty of her situation, Franklin stepped in to assist his old friend, further strengthening their bond. After Franklin left England on the even of the Revolution, he and Polly continued in regular correspondence, and after the Revolution ended, Polly arranged to renew their friendship face to face, visiting Franklin at Passy in 1785. In the following year, she followed him when he returned to Philadelphia, and was at Franklin's beside when he died in 1790. In his will, Franklin recognized Polly with a silver tankard he had "marked for her use during her life," acknowledging her daughter Eliza as well, and leaving books to her sons William and Thomas.
Related Archival Materials note
Other Benjamin Franklin Collections
Benjamin Franklin Papers
View Collection
Franklin-Bache
View Collection
Miscellaneous Benjamin Franklin Collections
View Collection
Early American History Note
The Bradford Collection contains a signficant portion of Franklin correspondence. It includes a miscellany of Franklin writings that includes things like vocabularies and a mock newspaper he composed in 1774. The bulk of the collection contains correspondence Franklin had with the Stevenson and Hewson families, especially with Polly Stevenson Hewson.
Bradford, William, 1719-1791; Cadwalader, John, 1742-1786; Hawkesworth, John, 1715?-1773; Henry, Patrick, 1736-1799; Hewson, Mary Stevenson, 1734-1795; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834; Washington, George, 1732-1799; American Revolution; Colonial Politics; Craven Street Gazette; Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Great Britain--Social life and customs--18th century; International Affairs; Marriage and Family Life; Social Life and Custom
- Franklin - Stevenson - Hewson Papers, 1749-1794; B F85.bra; 81 items
  - Opinion and conjectures..., 1749; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 6)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1760 January 14; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 10)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1760 June 6; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 11)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1760 June 23; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 12)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1760 [September]; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 13)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1760 September 16; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 14)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1761 January 13; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 15)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1761 April 27; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 16)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1761 May 19; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 17)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1761 July 8; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 18)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1761 July 30; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 19)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1761 September 10; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 20)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1761 November 9; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 21)
  - to Dr. John Hawkesworth, 1761 December 16; Stevenson, Mary (Folder 60)
  - to "dear cousin", 1761 December 17; Stevenson, Mary (Folder 67)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1762 March 10; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 22)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1762 June 11; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 23)
  - to Polly Stevenson Hewson, 1762 June 21; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 1)
  - to Mary Stevenson, 1762 July 25; Hawkesworth, Mrs. (Folder 68)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1762 August 5; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 24)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 March 11; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 25)
  - to Mary Stevenson, 1763 August 28; Hawkesworth, Mrs. (Folder 69)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 August 30; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 26)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 November 25; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 27)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 May 24; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 28)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1765 January 17; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 29)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1765 February 8; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 30)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1765 July 28; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 31)
  - to Polly Stevenson Hewson, [1765?] December 31; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 3)
  - Proposals..., 1766 January 16; Sun Fire-Office, Cornhill (Folder 79)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 March 9; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 32)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 September 26; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 33)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 November 22; Stevenson, Mrs. (Folder 51)
  - to Polly Stevenson Hewson, 1767 June 15; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 2)
  - to Deborah Franklin, 1767 September 18; Stevenson, Mrs. (Folder 55)
  - to Polly Stevenson Hewson, 1768 July 20; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 4)
  - [Scheme for a new alphabet...] Remarks, [1768]; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 7)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1769 December; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 34)
  - to Mary Stevenson, 1770 February 28; Hawkesworth, John, 1715?-1773 (Folder 72)
  - Marriage settlement of Mary Stevenson and William Hewson, 1770 July 9 (Folder 56)
  - Craven Street Gazette, 1770 Sept. 22-26; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 8)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 October 31; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 35)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1771 November 2; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 36)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 July 6; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 37)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 22; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 38)
  - Parable on brotherly love, [1774]; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 9)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 January 11; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 39)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 30; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 40)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 23; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 41)
  - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1782 March 27; Briscoe, A. (Folder 76)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, ca. 1782; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 41a)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 28; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 42)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 2; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 43)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 26; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 44)
    Scope and Contents note
    (also letter from J.Williams to BF)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 8; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 45)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 October 17; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 46)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 August 14; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 47)
  - Will, 1794 June 7; Hewson, Mary (Folder 57)
  - Notes on Matthew 13,30, n.d.; Fortin, John (Folder 77)
  - to Polly Stevenson Hewson, n.d.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 (Folder 5)
  - to Mary Stevenson, n.d.; Hawkesworth, John, 1715?-1773 (Folder 73)
  - to Mary Stevenson, n.d.; Hawkesworth, John, 1715?-1773 (Folder 74)
  - Miscellaneous notes - 5 pieces. Explanation of Proverbs 27, 14., n.d.; Hawkesworth, John, 1715?-1773 (Folder 75)
  - to Mrs. Lynn, n.d. (Friday night); Hewson, Mary (Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous notes - 3 pieces, n.d.; Hewson, Mary (Folder 78)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, n.d. (Friday night); Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 48)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, n.d.; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 49)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, n.d.; Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson) (Folder 50)
  - to Mary Stevenson, n.d.; Hawkesworth, Mrs. (Folder 70)
  - to Mary Stevenson, n.d.; Hawkesworth, Mrs. (Folder 71)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, n.d. (August 4 Tuesday evening); Stevenson, Mrs. (Folder 52)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, n.d. (August 5 Thursday); Stevenson, Mrs. (Folder 53)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, n.d.; Stevenson, Mrs. (Folder 54)
  - to Dr. John Hawkesworth, n.d.; Stevenson, Mary (Folder 61)
  - to Dr. John Hawkesworth, n.d.; Stevenson, Mary (Folder 62)
  - to Dr. John Hawkesworth, n.d.; Stevenson, Mary (Folder 63)
  - to Dr. John Hawkesworth, n.d.; Stevenson, Mary (Folder 64)
  - to Dr. John Hawkesworth, n.d.; Stevenson, Mary (Folder 65)
  - to Dr. John Hawkesworth, n.d.; Stevenson, Mary (Folder 66)
  - to Mrs. Margaret Stevenson, n.d. (Sunday evening); Stevenson, Mary (Folder 58)
- Transcripts of Hewson-Franklin Correspondence, 1758-1898; B F85.bra1; 38 items
  - to Charles [S.] Bradford, 1898 March 30; Ford, Paul L. (Folder 1)
  - to Charles [S.] Bradford, 1898 July 15; Ford, Paul L. (Folder 2)
  - Introduction. .George Gulliver, n.d.; Hewson, William. (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (Folder 4)
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1758 Aug. 20; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1760 Feb. 14; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1761 July 7; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1762 May 10; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1762 May 24; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1762 June 21; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1763 June 27; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1764 May 4; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, [1764 Dec.]; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1765 Jan. 9; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, [1765? Dec. 31; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1767 March 26; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, [1767?] May 16; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1767 May 16; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1768 Oct. 20; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1770 July 18; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1772 July 8; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1780 Jan. 10; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1780 Dec. 7; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1782 May 13; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, [1782?]; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1783 Jan. 8; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1783 July 12; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1784 Jan. 1; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1784 April 29; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, June 15; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, Wednesday morning; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, Wednesday P.M; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, Friday morning; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, Friday 2 P.M; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mary Stevenson Hewson, n.d.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - Marriage settlement, 1770; Hewson, Mary.
    - to Brown, Collinson, etc, 1780 Jan. 10; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Woodmason, 1780 Jan. 10; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    - to Mr. Viny, 1784 May 10; Hewson, Mary.
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts, 1777-1896; B F85.bra2; 10 items
  - to [Philemon] Dickinson, 1777 August 27; Washington, George, 1732-1799 (Folder 1)
  - to Thomas [Bradford], 1779 May 4; Bradford, William, Jr. (Folder 2)
  - Letter of administration of Margaret Stevenson's estate to Mary Stevenson Hewson, 1783 January 16; Robert, bishop of London. (Folder 3)
  - to [John] Cadwallader [sic], 1784 December 11; Washington, George, 1732-1799 (Folder 4)
  - to [Mrs. Sarah Franklin Ba]che, 1785 April 13; Hewson, Mary (Folder 5)
  - Declaration of trust of estate of Mary Hewson, 1796 November 2; Blunt, James. (Folder 6)
  - La Fayette - a song, 1824 September 6; Bradford, William, 1719-1791 (Folder 7)
  - to Charles S. Bradford, 1896 September 21; Hart, Charles Henry (Folder 8)
  - to [John] Cadwalader, n.d.; Henry, Patrick, 1736-1799 (Folder 9)
  - to [John] Cadwalader, n.d. (Thursday morning); Henry, Patrick, 1736-1799 (Folder 10)